Alison Myers

<u>alisonlouisemyers@gmail.com</u> | (778) 928-7726 portfolio: alisonlouisemyers.com

Accomplished Data Analyst with 10 years of experience designing and implementing analytics solutions, managing ETL processes, and developing advanced data visualizations. Proven ability to lead projects, communicate complex technical concepts, and enhance data accuracy and accessibility. Highly skilled with **SQL**, **Python**, **Tableau**, and data modeling, with a track record of successful stakeholder engagement and project management.

EMPLOYMENT

The University of British Columbia

2014 - Present

Programmer Analyst

Centre for Teaching Learning & Technology

Sept 2023 – Present

- Designs and implements comprehensive analytics solutions, conducting advanced data analysis and
 modeling to uncover trends and patterns; creates custom reproducible reports, informative dashboards
 and supplementary materials. Actively involved in developing, testing, documenting, and promoting
 analytics software in collaboration with teammates.
- Develops and maintains ETL processes, ensuring data accuracy and consistency through rigorous validation, quality assurance, and system testing.
- Develops ad-hoc and customized SQL queries to fulfill diverse data requests, write scripts (Python) for summarizing reports, and create replicable report templates using scripting to enhance data consistency and accessibility.
- Communicates clearly with clients and stakeholders to gather requirements, develop and implement project plans, and provide quality data or products to meet a diverse range of needs.
- Manages and prioritizes multiple software development and data analysis projects, ensuring clear and effective communication of complex technical concepts to non-technical stakeholders. Oversees the complete production life cycle, from software design and testing to final deployment and documentation.
- Leads the UBC Learning Analytics/Visual Analytics community of practice to foster relationships with the common goal of promoting awareness and adoption of analytics within the institution.
- Stays up-to-date with industry trends and emerging technologies in analytics and data visualization to continually enhance personal expertise and organizational capability.

Senior Data Analyst

Jan 2023 – Aug 2023

UBC Sauder School of Business

- Led and managed end-to-end analytics projects, including stakeholder consultation, development of compelling business cases, and creation of detailed project plans. Effectively controlled project scope, timelines, and deliverables, ensuring clear communication with all client segments.
- Created and maintained dynamic dashboards and reports, utilizing advanced programming skills in **Tableau** and **Python** to develop data visualizations that effectively communicate insights.
- Implemented advanced technologies to ensure replicability and maintained high documentation standards across all projects, enhancing data integrity and usability for future reporting and analysis.

Research Analyst

UBC Sauder School of Business

Jan 2017 – Dec 2022

- Championed a culture of data-first initiatives, empowering instructors and senior leadership to leverage
 data for the strategic evaluation of educational programming, enhancing decision-making and program
 effectiveness.
- Established an innovative open-source framework using **APIs, Python, Jupyter**, and **GitHub**, leading to the development of over 30 tools that automated manual workflows and significantly boosted analytics awareness and adoption.
- Engineered and implemented robust workflows and programs for extracting, cleaning, and transforming
 data from diverse educational platforms. Utilized APIs and data processing while integrating GitHub as a
 key distribution and collaboration platform. Ensured comprehensive documentation and reporting to
 provide actionable insights to stakeholders and leadership.

Data Analytics Specialist

Sept 2014 - Dec 2016

UBC Sauder School of Business

- Identified and championed the integration of learning analytics within the school, advocating for its adoption by the Learning Services educational technology team. Collaborated closely with the Director and Senior leadership to establish and define the role, setting a foundation for enhanced educational analysis.
- Pioneered the introduction and led the sponsorship of modern reporting solutions, facilitating the successful adoption of Tableau Desktop and Tableau Server across the organization. This initiative significantly improved data visualization capabilities and decision-making processes.
- Revolutionized quarterly evaluation reporting by developing an automated system using R, RMarkdown, and LaTeX, which streamlined data management workflows and enhanced report accuracy and accessibility.

COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP

LAVA Community Leader, UBC

2015 – present

• Leads the <u>Learning Analytics/Visual Analytics</u> (LAVA) community of practice at UBC which fosters relationships across faculties with the common goal of promoting awareness and adoption of analytics in the institution. Over 5 years of regular monthly knowledge sharing and development sessions with regular audiences of 15-20.

Hackathon (Learning Analytics), UBC

2015 – present

• Planned and hosted 10+ <u>Learning Analytics hackathons</u> and workshops to give students hands-on experience tacking real world data challenges and to raise awareness of Learning Analytics. These semi-annual events regularly attract 100+ students.

PUBLICATIONS & PRESENTATIONS

Thompson, C., Myers, A., Lee, J., & Engle, W. (2024). Hackathons for awareness and community engagement in learning analytics. In *Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference on Learning Analytics & Knowledge*, 41-44. https://www.solaresearch.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/LAK24_CompanionProceedings.pdf

Cho, S., Werker, G. R., Myers, A., Prodanovic, M., & Huh, W. T. (2024). Video Analytics: When and How Do Students Use Asynchronous Videos? Using the COVID-19 Experience to Reimagine Teaching. In *Online Learning, Open Education, and Equity in a Post-Pandemic*. (In press)

Macfadyen, L. P., & Myers, A. (2023). The "IKEA Model" for pragmatic development of a custom learning analytics dashboard. *ASCILITE Publications*, 482–486. https://doi.org/10.14742/apubs.2023.465

EDUCATION

Master of Educational Technology, University of British Columba	2022
Bachelor of Arts , Cognitive Systems, University of British Columbia	2015
Bachelor of Science , Honours Psychology, University of Waterloo	2012